醒醒
Wake up.
醒醒 我的宝贝儿
Wake up, sleepyhead.
又把被单抢走了 你这野人
怎么那么多噩梦
你还得为之付出代价
安静点 女人
Be quiet, woman.
波士卡
Posca.
卢修斯 乌利纳斯
Lucius Vorenus.
你每月一次的放纵就结束了？
Your monthly debauch is finished already?
我看你的还没结束
I see yours isn't.
我这样？这不算什么放纵
This? This is nothing.
这是放松
This is for my nerves.
- 他在哪儿 - 噢 他在哪儿
- Where is he? - Where is he?
噢 很深奥的问题
A deep question.
他在皇宫大殿
His mortal flesh is in the throne room
会见元老院的代表团
meeting the delegation from the Senate.
- 他们已经来了？- 是的
- They're here already? - Yes.
毕布路斯议员和其他一些 我记不得名字的达官贵人
Senator Bibulus and several other distinguished men whose names I forget
今早抵达的
arrived this morning.
那你怎么不在里面
And why are you not in there?
我非常地珍惜自己的生命
I value my life, such as it is.
女王对我咆哮的时候 我退出了
When the queen growls at me, I retreat.
这可不是懦弱
It's not cowardice.
我死了谁来照顾我的妻子？
Who would look after my wife?
瞄准动物的前面一点 明白吗
You lead the animal on slightly. You see?
要配合它的速度
Depending on how fast he's going.
喝水
Drink the water.
就是这个时候 动物只感到口渴
Now here's the moment. The animal thinks only of his thirst.
它知道有危险
He knows there is danger.
却不能抵抗水的诱惑
But he cannot resist the water.
你看 很简单
Easy, you see.
我来试试
My turn.
安东尼 我们能谈谈眼下的问题吗
Antony, if we might discuss the matter at hand?
你会把小鹿吓跑的
You'll scare off the deer.
- 它动了 那野兽动了 - 再来一次
- He moved. The beast moved! - Again.
关于粮食供应…
Regarding the grain supply...
上头同意付给你之前两倍的价格
I have been authorized to offer you double the previous price,
只要你保证月底前交货
if you can guarantee delivery before the end of the month.
你说两倍？
Double, you say?
不错啊
That's not bad.
- 三倍 - 成交
- Triple. - Agreed.
我们会照定价的三倍支付
We will pay triple the correct price.
还有迦太基
And Carthage.
将迦太基划入安东尼治下
Carthage will be annexed to Antony's control.
那 或许是可行的
That may be possible.
可怜的屋大维 嗯？
Poor Octavian.
他一定会非常绝望
He must be really desperate.
人民正遭受饥荒 饿殍满地
People are starving, dying.
屋大维会尽一切可能 阻止饥荒的蔓延
Octavian will do what he must to prevent further suffering.
因为他是那么的热爱他的人民
Because he loves the people so.
- 是的 - 他谁也不爱 也没人爱他
- He does. - He loves nobody and nobody loves him.
他可以用云雀和牡蛎 喂饱他的人民
He could feed the people larks and oysters till they burst,
然而他们 还是会更爱我
and they would still love me more.
对吗 乌利纳斯
Isn't that right, Vorenus?
是的 长官
Yes, sir.
我们 代表人民的心声
There we are. The voice of the people.
他们爱我
They love me.
我相信您是对的 不过我们有个协议 对吗
I have no doubt you are right, but we do have an agreement, yes?
对
Yes.
三倍的价格…
Triple rates...
和迦太基
and Carthage.
- 还有西班牙 - 西班牙？
- And Spain. - Spain?
你不能要西班牙 噢？
You can't have Spain.
噢 真遗憾 交易失败
That's a shame. No deal, then.
- 真的 这简直是… - 交易 失败
- Really, this is absolutely... - No deal.
噢 太好了 亲爱的
Brava, my love!
晚餐吃鹿肉 怎样
Venison for dinner, then?
一路平安 朋友
Pleasant voyage home, boys.
把他弄出去
Get him out of here.
我带你去看看你的住所
I'll show you to your quarters.
- 他总是那样吗 - 哪样？
- Is he always like that? - Like what?
如果这样都不能让那小混蛋宣战
Well, if that doesn't make the little shit declare war,
真不知道还有什么办法了
I don't know what will.
他是只很谨慎的野兽
He's a cautious beast.
或许你该割断绳子
Perhaps you should simply cut the cord
主动宣战
and declare war yourself.
宣战…
Declare war...
向屋大维？
on Octavian?
我最信任最热爱的同僚？
On my most trusted and beloved colleague?
向罗马？向我的人民？不 不 不
On Rome? On my own people? No, no, no.
不 不行
No, that wouldn't do.
我会作为一个救世主
When I return home,
而不是征服者回到家乡
it will be as a savior, not as a conqueror.
我很累了
I'm very tired.
海洛斯
Oh, Helios.
塞勒涅 快出去 快出去
Selene, off with you. Off with you.
没看见你们父亲要睡觉吗
Can't you see your father needs to sleep?
你要去哪儿 别走
Where are you going? Stay.
你也听到他们在吵闹
You can hear them.
你想怎么办 给他们烤个蛋糕？
What are you gonna do? Bake 'em a cake?
噢 该死啊
Oh, Dis.
有时我会忘记你是个 多么冷血的妓女
I forget sometimes what a cold-hearted bitch you really are.
我要不是这样 你还会要我吗？
Would you have me any other way?
你在开玩笑吗
Are you joking?
只要有人给我一匹 配上皮鞍的好马…
Anyone offers me a good horse with the leathers thrown in...
你就不会在这儿了
...you're gone.
后退 后退
Back! Back!
让开 别挡路
Keep out of the way! Get out of the way!
让他过来
Let me through.
闪一边去
Get out the way!
让开
Clear the way.
粮食 粮食 粮食 粮食
Grain! Grain! Grain! Grain!
- 行行好 - 我父亲快饿死了
- Please! - My father is starving.
求求了 我父亲…
Please! My father...
安静
Silence.
Silence!
今天的配给已经发放了
The day's ration has been given.
明天指定时间之前不会再有
There'll be no more until tomorrow at the appointed time.
不要啊
No!
我知道你们很饿
I know you're hungry.
但你们还活着
But you're alive.
如果我同意你们所求 开仓放赈
If I do as you ask and open the granaries,
你们今天能饱餐一顿 明天就要饿死
you'll be well fed today and starving tomorrow.
回家吧
Go home.
回家吧 接受大地母亲 给我们的安排
Go home and suffer what the Earth Mother has sent us.
明天再来
And come back tomorrow.
好了
Right.
还是完整的啊 还以为你会被他们吃了
Still in one piece, then? Thought they might have ate you.
我身上的软骨太多了 他们不喜欢
Too much gristle on the bone.
卢修斯 女孩儿们 我跟你们说过在里面等
Lucius, girls, I thought I told you to wait inside.
即便血溅当场 我也不怕 那不是很光荣吗？
I'll not cower when there's blood to be spilled. Where's the honor in that?
毛长齐了再来说你怕不怕
When you have hair on your chin you can talk of blood.
乌利娜 我原本期望更高 下次照吩咐去做
Vorena, I expected better. Next time do as you're told.
都是挨饿的人们 不会伤害我们
They're just hungry people. They'd not hurt us.
饿极了的人什么都做得出来
Hungry people do strange things.
神圣的奥博娜女神会保护我们的
Then blessed Orbona will protect us.
好吧 你去找她给我们送船粮食来
Well, run along and ask her to send a grain ship.
我和马修斯有事要谈
Me and Mascius have to talk.
你也去 卢修斯
You too, Lucius.
学学朗读什么的
Go learn to read or something.
- 还有多少 - 还剩十天 大概四分之一的配给量
- What's the tally? - Ten days left, a quarter ration, give or take.
- 我的死神啊 - 几乎不够分发的
- Gods below. - It's hardly worth giving out.
只是延长痛苦而已
Just prolonging the misery.
早上好
Morning.
面包师行会的人一早就来了
The bakers' guild man was round earlier.
我跟你说过别理他们
I told you not to speak to them.
我没有
Nor did I.
只是他说 我什么都没说
He spoke, I said nothing.
他们出价600一袋
They're offering 600 a sack.
600？
600?
是啊 600和那么多死去的孩子
Yeah, 600 and a few dead children
没有一袋能到达真正 需要它们的人手中
for every sack that doesn't get to the people that need them.
我们不赚这缺德钱
We're not in this for profit.
可是 那是600
Still, it's 600.
去他妈的面包师行会
I piss on the bakers' guild.
- 你说了算 - 是的 我说了算
- Your call. - Yes, it is.
你干嘛还在他身上 浪费宝贵的食物
Why are you wasting valuable food on him still?
让那混蛋死了吧
Let the poor bastard die.
摩密奥？
Memmio?
不 他能提醒其他人保持忠诚
No. He reminds the other men to stay honest.
那我们要怎么办
What's to be done, then?
拿我最好的衣服来 我去看看执政官有什么主意
Fetch my best clothes. I'll see if his honor has any ideas.
嘿
Hey!
你 安静
Quiet, you.
你这该死的混蛋
You fucking hairy bastard.
到目前为止 死的都是老人和病人
So far it's just the old and the sick that are dying.
但是到下个月 谷仓就要空了
But by next moon, our granaries will be empty.
我听说狗肉挺好吃的
I understand that dogs make good eating.
是的
They do.
如果烹调方法对吃起来就像猪肉一样 早就没有狗了
Taste like pork if you cook 'em right. All gone.
啊 难怪我说晚上怎么能那么安宁
I wondered why the nights were so peaceful.
- 没有犬吠声 - 现在不是开玩笑的时候
- No barking. - This is no moment for wit.
我希望我能做些什么
I wish there were something I could do.
但是国家粮仓跟 你们的一样几近空虚
But the state granaries are near as empty as yours.
除非我从别人那儿抢来给你
I can only give to you by taking from someone else.
- 军库还没开封 - 军队也需要粮食维持
- The military silos are untapped. - And the army needs to eat.
那么 派三个军团到非洲去
Well, then, send three legions to Africa.
让李必达养他们
Let Lepidus feed them.
这样一来 就能保证 城市里一个月的用粮
That would supply the city with enough grain for a month.
就这样办
Have it done.
这只是暂时的解决办法 我们已尽了最大努力
It's only a temporary solution, but it's the best we can offer.
- 我会把能省下的送去给你  - 谢谢您
- I'll send you what we can spare. - Thank you.
波罗
Pullo.
告诉我 人们怎么说
Tell me what the people are saying.
告诉我 他们把这次饥荒 怪罪到谁的头上
Tell me who they blame for this famine.
他们说 是您
You, they say.
- 您是当权者 - 不是安东尼？
- You're the man in charge. - Not Antony?
他们听说了
They hear the newsreaders saying
他阻断一切货运往来
that he's holding back the shipments and all that, but...
可是 他是安东尼啊 不是吗
well, it's Antony, innit?
他为什么要让他们挨饿
Why would he starve them?
他们一直都很爱戴他 他也一直享受着他们的爱戴
They've always loved him and he's always loved to be loved.
然而您…
Whereas you...
嗯 您就是您 不是吗
Well, you're you, aren't you?
冷血无情？
Cold and heartless?
我没这么说
I'll not say that.
但是您的感情从不外露 现在呢
But you've never been the affectionate type now, have you?
谢谢你 波罗
Thank you, Pullo.
- 我会得到粮食的消息 对吗 - 阿格里帕负责这事
- I'll be hearing about the grain, then, will I? - Agrippa will see to it.
- 可能毕布路斯会成功 - 不 他不会
- Perhaps Bibulus will succeed? - No, he won't.
安东尼还没完全失去理智 给够他钱 他还能拒绝？
Antony's not entirely irrational. Given enough money, why should he refuse?
安东尼不会为钱动心
Antony's not motivated by money.
他想要激怒人民起来推翻我
He hopes the people will rise up in anger and depose me.
要不然 他就只想 挑拨我对他发动战争
Either that, or he simply wishes to provoke me into declaring war on him.
他真的变得这么愚蠢了吗
Has he really become so foolish?
在那里待了那么多年 谁知道他变成什么样儿了
Who knows what he's become after all these years out there?
谁知道克娄巴特拉 给他吹了什么枕边风
Who knows what Cleopatra whispers to him?
碰到女人 他就变笨
He was always a fool for his women.
如果他想开战 为什么不满足他
If he wants a war, why not give it to him?
哼 你听到波罗说了
You heard Pullo.
那等于是向美酒和歌舞宣战
You might as well declare war on wine and song.
不 不 不
No, no, no, no.
与安东尼一战在所难免 除非人民站在我们这一边
War on Antony is doomed unless the people are with us.
把我母亲和姐姐接来
Send for my mother and sister.
今晚我该与她们一起吃晚餐
I shall have dinner with them this evening.
外婆
Grandma?
你不该来这儿
You shouldn't be here.
这儿很危险
It's dangerous.
安东尼娅 你在哪儿
Antonia, where are you?
她跟我在这 我带她下去
She's up here with me. I'll bring her down.
你这个调皮的孩子
You naughty girl.
我跟你说过别到屋顶上去
What have I told you about going on the roof?
我向黛安娜女神起誓 我会找人打她一顿
I swear on Diana, I shall have someone beat her.
她根本不听我的话
She doesn't listen to a word I say.
噢 她是个好女孩 真的 跟你小时候一样
She's a good girl, really. Just like you were at that age.
我长大了却这么斯文？
And I turned out so well?
而你弟弟 小时候 跟小狗一样听话
Your brother, on the other hand, was as biddable as a shepherd's dog.
从来不惹麻烦
No trouble at all.
卡斯托 今天有我的信吗
Castor, are there any letters for me today?
没有 夫人
No, Domina.
奇怪
Strange.
我有强烈的感觉就是今天
I had the strongest feeling that today was the day.
母亲 不会有信来的
Mother? There will be no letter.
你错了
You're wrong.
恕我直言 可是…
Sorry to be blunt, but...
你不认为该面对现实了吗
Well, don't you think it's time to face facts?
安东尼答应他会来接我 他就一定会来
Antony promised to send for me and he will.
就算他来了 你以为 屋大维会放你走？
Even if he did, do you think Octavian would let you go?
我才不管他
I don't give a fig.
说真的 他值得你这样折磨自己吗
Truly, is he worth torturing yourself like this?
夫人 屋大维 恺撒传令你们俩 今晚与他共进晚餐
Domina? Octavian Caesar summons you both for dinner this evening.
我想知道 这次他又想要什么
What does he want now, I wonder?
肯定对我们没好处
Nothing to our benefit.
家人和朋友 呃？
Family and friends.
没有比这更好的了
Nothing better.
屋达维娅 我想请你帮个忙
Octavia, I have a favor to ask of you.
我想你已经知道我们粮食短缺
You are aware of the grain shortage, I suppose?
你知道人们无以为继 横尸街头
You know that the people are dying in the streets for want of bread?
而你想让我来养他们？
And you want me to feed them?
不妨这样说
In a manner of speaking.
你丈夫在埃及有大量的粮食
Your husband has plenty of grain in Egypt.
但他在耍政治手段 阻止其流通
But he is playing politics with it, holding it back.
如果你去跟他谈谈…
If you were to go and talk to him...
我？去埃及？
I? Go to Egypt?
轻柔的嗓音是作为一位
The soft voice of a loving wife
可爱的妻子的首要条件
may succeed where all else has failed.
你在开玩笑
You are joking?
我都不记得我上次开玩笑是在什么时候了
I cannot remember the last time I made a joke.
上次市集日
Last market day.
你说了鱼什么的 我笑得肚子疼
You said something about fishes which made me laugh quite distinctly.
我是在打比方
I was speaking figuratively.
如果你认真的 去的应该是母亲而不是我 她才是他真正的妻子
If you are serious, it is not I should go, but Mother. She's his real wife.
我想你也一起去
I thought you might go together.
亲自向安东尼证实
Present Antony with both reality and appearance.
那很好 可是…
That's all very well, but...
我不想坐船千里迢迢地去找他
I have no desire to take a long sea voyage.
- 你觉得呢 - 我也不想
- Do you? - No.
再说了 我们又不饿
Besides, we're not hungry.
我们也不需要粮食
And we need no grain.
这对我们有什么好处？
So what's in it for us?
你怎么补偿我们？
How will you pay us for our trouble?
你们想要怎样？
What do you want?
庞培已经没落
Pompeii's become vulgar.
我想在卡普里要一座别墅
I'd like a villa in Capri.
没问题
That's fine.
你呢 屋达维娅 你想要别墅吗
What about you, Octavia? Do you want a villa?
嗯 我不知道
I don't know.
有座别墅挺不错的
A villa would be nice.
要是再来几个角斗士就更好了
Some gladiators would be fun as well.
为什么不要现金 以后再做决定？
Why not take cash and decide later?
- 好主意 现金 - 如你所愿
- Good idea. Cash. - As you wish.
米西奈斯 让新闻发言人 \宣布她们会尽早离开
Maecenas, have the newsreader announce they are leaving as soon as possible.
我喜欢小鸟
I like birds.
不喜欢鸟蛋 我觉得鸟蛋很脏
I don't like eggs. There is something quite sordid about eggs.
我们不该继续养它们了 当然 除非你反对
We shan't serve them anymore. Unless you object, of course.
你为什么要让阿提娅 和屋达维娅去埃及
Why are you sending Atia and Octavia to Egypt?
- 你听到我说的了 - 噢 是的 但那不是真正的原因
- You heard why. - Well, yes, but that can't be the real reason.
你知道安东尼一定 会拒绝她们的要求
You know Antony will refuse what they ask.
很有可能
It's very likely.
怎么
What?
你算计着… 如果安东尼拒绝屋达维娅
You calculate... that if Antony turns Octavia away,
人们会认为他公然 侮辱了他亲爱的妻子
the people will feel that he has publicly humiliated his darling wife,
克娄巴特拉女王迷惑了他
that Queen Cleopatra has bewitched him,
他们会开始反对他
and they will all turn against him.
差不多
Something like that.
另一种可能是
But on the other hand,
如果安东尼还爱着阿提娅 屈服与她的请求
if Antony still loves Atia and yields to her pleading,
那就更好了
then... so much the better.
你会得到你想要的粮食
You'll have your grain.
聪明的小伙子
Clever boy.
晚安 亲爱的
Good night, my dear.
我希望你别走了
I wish you'd stop that.
我们不会因此而早到
We'll get there no faster.
你觉得 我变了吗 自他上次见我之后
Have I changed at all, do you think, since he last saw me?
没有 你跟从前一模一样
No. You're just exactly as you were.
他会在极度兴奋中投入你的怀抱
He'll fall into your arms in a delirium of love.
你说真的吗
Do you mean that?
不
No.
你越来越刻薄了 你知道 刻薄又苦闷
You've become very mean, you know. Mean and bitter.
你越来越像个小女孩般多愁善感
You've become girlish and sentimental.
坦白的说 很恶心
It's disgusting, frankly.
不得分 不得分
No points. No points.
我还没准备好
I wasn't ready.
我得十分
Ten points to me.
很好 殿下 很好
Well done, Majesty. Well done.
- 准备好了吗 - 没有 等一下
- Ready? - No, wait!
求您了 等一下
I beg thee! Wait!
跟老女人一样没用 滚
Useless old woman. Go away.
乌利纳斯 陪我玩
Vorenus, play with me.
认真点
Throw it properly.
那么 来吧
Come on, then.
接得好
Good catch.
再跟我说说我父亲的事
Tell me more about my father.
我知道的都告诉你了
I told you all that I know.
你跟我说的连傻瓜都知道
You've told me only what every fool knows.
他是个伟大的战士 人民爱戴他 等等等等
He was a great soldier, the people loved him, blah blah blah.
告诉我 作为一个人 他是怎样的
Tell me what he was like as a man.
嗯 他…
Well, he was...
他是个好人
he was a good man.
他是个很好的朋友
He was a good man to have as a friend.
你不会想与他为敌
You wouldn't want him as an enemy.
被激怒的时候 他的脾气很不好
He had a nasty temper when he was roused.
如果战局陷入困境 其他人开始退缩
When the battle was going hard and men were faltering,
你会希望有你的父亲站在你这边
that's when you'd want to see your father at your side.
他是我所知的最勇敢的人
Bravest man I've ever known.
还有呢
More.
骑马好手
Fine horseman.
笨蛋赌徒 可是他从不承认
Bad gambler, though he'd never admit it.
他喜欢美女
He liked the women.
他喜欢美食
He liked to eat.
如果你不阻止他 他能把整桌菜吃掉
He'd eat the whole table if you'd let him.
真的吗
Really?
我一直听说他… 饮食有度
I've always heard he was very... abstemious in his diet.
是的 嗯 那是对的
Yeah, well, that would be right.
有人比我更了解他
There's others knew him far better than I did.
- 他们在哪儿 - 怎么了
- Where are they? - What's wrong?
什么意思 来这里？
What do you mean, here?
她们的船一个小时前就靠岸了
Their ship docked an hour ago.
她们现在在来皇宫的路上
They're on their way to the palace now.
她们还要求立即与您会面
And they request an immediate audience with you!
真有趣
How delicious.
妻子和情人一同来看你
Wife and lover come together to see you.
安静 女人
Hush, woman.
- 她们想要什么 - 我不知道
- What do they want? - I don't know.
我该怎么跟她们说 她们马上就到了
What shall I tell them? They will be here.
给我… 给我…
Just, give... give...
给我时间想想
give me time to think.
不
No.
她们不会是自己要来的
They would not have come of their own accord.
一定是屋大维派她们来的
Octavian must have sent them here.
派她们来做什么
Sent them to do what?
噢 为什么派我的妻子来
Why else send my wife
除非是想达成某种
except to effect some kind of...
和解
reconciliation.
- 那你该拒绝她 - 当然
- Well, you must refuse her. - Obviously, yes.
但是...
But that...
那正中他的下怀
that is exactly what he wants.
他强迫我做一个公开的选择
He is forcing me to choose publicly
在她...和你之间的
between her and... and you.
如果我把她赶走… 我也许真会这样
And when I turn her away, which I will,
他就有了开战的理由
he will have his premise for war.
那又怎样？
Then why so glum?
这不正是你一直期望的吗 他挑起的战争
You have what you wanted. A war that he will start,
而不是你在无理取闹
a war that you did not seek.
但是 我...
And still...
我不喜欢这样
I do not like it.
哈 他...
He is...
他是从人民手中
he is striking
取代我的影响力
at my support amongst the people.
他...他会认为 他从策略上战胜了我
He... he will think he has outmaneuvered me.
那又怎样？是非在乎实力
What matter? As long as you win the war.
对
Yes.
- 希望如此 - 无论如何...
- I suppose so. - In any case...
我们不能拒人千里 是吧？
we must be gracious hosts, ne?
我们要请她们吃喝玩乐
We shall throw a lovely party for them.
查米恩 叫厨房主管过来
Charmian, send for the kitchen chamberlain.
不 不 不 不
No, no, no. No!
不？我们得热情点
No? We must be hospitable.
你喜欢这样 是吧
You'd love that, wouldn't you?
羞辱阿提亚
Humiliating Atia.
你扮演女王 看着她痛苦
Watching her squirm as you play the queen.
扮演女王？
Play the queen?
我就是女王
I am a queen.
- 你知道我的意思 - 不 不 我不知道
- You know what I mean. - No. No, I don't.
你…你只是想 在她面前炫耀我们的爱罢了
You... you just want to flaunt our love in front of her.
为什么不呢？我们互相爱着对方 不是吗
Why not? We love each other, don't we?
而且 你也不再爱她了
And you no longer love her.
为什么不该让她知道？
Why should she not know it?
这是一个善举
It's an act of kindness.
让她不再对你朝思暮想
Stop her pining for you.
我没说错啊 你不再爱她了
I'm not wrong, am I? You do no longer love her.
当然 我不再爱她了
Of course I no longer love her.
你知道我不再爱她了
And you know I no longer love her.
但她也不该受到当众羞辱
But neither do I think she deserves public humiliation.
这就是重点
That is the whole point.
这就是为什么他们来这儿 为了被羞辱
That is why they're here, to be humiliated.
不 我认为她不知道
No, I don't think she knows that.
也不会来这儿
Else she would not be here.
我想她那混帐儿子
I think her fucking son
已经在控制她了
has manipulated her into it.
那就杀掉她们
Let's kill them, then.
什么 你刚才说了什么
What? What did you say?
阿提亚不会受到羞辱...
Atia will not be humiliated...
因为她就要死了
because Atia will be dead.
屋大维会知道你不是那种 他可以超越的人
Octavian will know that you're not a man to be outmaneuvered.
太棒了
It's perfect.
不 我的人会把我当成弑妻者 而看低我
No. My people will despise me as a wife-killer.
那他们的船就会驶回去了
Well, their ship sank on the way home.
- 不 - 这很正常的
- No. - It happens all the time.
不 我讨厌这样 不
No. I mean it. No!
我明白了 你是个懦夫
I see. Well, either you are a coward...
要不 你就是对她还有感情
or you still have feelings for her.
是哪个原因？
Which is it?
到底是为什么？
你为什么不能闭上你那该死的嘴？
Why don't you shut your fucking mouth?
哦 你...
Oh, you...
天哪 真是个可怕的地方
Gods, what a ghastly place.
很大 但
Big, though.
很粗俗
It's a sure sign of vulgarity.
托勒密原来是牧羊的 你知道吗
Ptolemies were originally goatherds, you know?
为什么这些门不开
Why are the doors not open?
够了
Enough!
不
No!
真可恶
This is outrageous.
无礼
The rudeness.
粗俗
It just goes to show... vulgar.
事实上 是皇权
Royalty, indeed.
太热了
This heat's unbearable.
我想我快晕了
I think I'm going to faint.
你想让他们给我拿点水来
You would think they would bring us water.
- 为什么不回到船里去 - 当然不行
- Can't we go back to the ship? - Absolutely not.
我就一直在这等着 直到那些恶心的人出来
We're staying here until these wretched people...
该死的
Oh, and about bloody time.
你好
Hello.
伊俄卡斯特 是你吗
Jocasta. Is it you?
当然是我 不然是谁呢
Of course it's me. Who else would I be?
你怎么了 这个吗
What's happened to you?
女王不喜欢罗马女人的装扮
This? Her Majesty doesn't like the Roman style on her women.
如果你问我的话 我是有点失去理智了
Quite irrational about the subject if you ask me.
但都是为了能过太平日子啊 我还挺喜欢现在这个样子
But anything for a quiet life. I rather like it now.
你来这儿干嘛？过这"假惺惺"的日子？
What are you doing here? Have you come for Crocodile Day?
我是这么叫它的 我不会说方言
That's what I call it, anyway. I can't get my mouth round their lingo.
她会大叫
She will shriek.
而我呢 就假装有点不正常 她就会让我走了
But I just pretend I'm a little mad, and she leaves off.
为什么门是关着的 为什么没人出来迎接我们
Why is the door kept shut? Why is there no one here to greet us?
我想一会就会有人来了
Oh, I'm sure there'll be someone along in a while.
世事变迁...这里变动不大 高温
Things move... ever so slow around here. It's the heat.
听着 你为什么不进去 告诉安东尼我们在等着见他？
Listen, why don't you go inside and tell Antony that we're waiting to see him?
很显然 他不知道我们在这儿
Obviously, he's not been informed that we're here.
我不能这样做
I couldn't do that.
不经她同意 任何人不得见安东尼
No one's allowed to speak to Antony without she says so.
除了我的波士卡
Except my dear little Posca.
当然还有卢修斯 乌利纳斯
And Lucius Vorenus, of course.
我喜欢你这样的头发
I love your hair like that.
现在人们都像这样吗
Is that how people are wearing it now?
谢天谢地 波士卡
Thank Juno. Posca.
- 她叫什么名字？- 伊俄卡斯特 你在干什么？
- What in heaven's name is... - Jocasta, what are you doing?
- 我只是… - 安静点
- I was only... - Quiet, woman!
波士卡 安东尼在哪
Posca, where's Antony?
是 是 很乐意效劳
Yes, yes! A great pleasure.
真的 走
Indeed, yes. Come along.
波士卡？波士卡？
Posca? Posca?
谢谢
Thank you.
他们都疯了
They've all gone insane, obviously.
太热了
So hot.
你知道的 这是为以后能更好
It's for the best, you know.
这样的宫廷生活对你不利
This palace life is no good for you.
你要有所行动
You need action.
是
Yeah.
当战争打起时 你会愈加开心
You'll be much more happy when the war begins.
- 乌利纳斯 - 头
- Vorenus. - Sir?
我给你个特别任务
I have a delicate mission for you.
我很开心看到至少你还没有回归自然
I'm glad to see you haven't gone native, at least.
也许你能讲出点道理来
Perhaps you can talk some sense.
这些人都怎么了
What is the matter with these people?
为什么没告诉安东尼我们来了
Why hasn't Antony been told of our arrival?
我由三人执政官之一马克.安东尼授权 护送你们回到船里
I've been ordered by Triumvir Mark Antony to escort you both back to your ship,
确认你们在风力允许的时候离开亚历山大
and to make sure that you leave Alexandria as soon as the wind allows.
都见不着他？
Without seeing him?
他撵走他孩子的母亲？
He turns away the mother of his child?
是的
That's correct.
是不是她让你这么做的？
It was she who ordered you to do this, wasn't it?
安东尼不会这么慢的
Antony wouldn't act so low.
我只是服从马克.安东尼的命令 女士
I take orders only from Mark Antony, madam.
不 我们不走
No, we're not going.
- 妈妈 我... - 女士？
- Mother, I... - Madam...
我们不走
We are not going.
我不会离开这里
I am not moving from this spot
除非安东尼他自己出来让我走
unless Antony comes down himself and tells me to go.
如果你不愿意走的话 我已经被授权
If you will not go willingly, I have been given orders
可采取任何必须手段让你们离开
to use whatever force necessary to remove you.
你将肆意粗暴对待朱利家的女人吗？
You would manhandle the women of the Julii?
不 但这儿的男人们
No, but these men here...
他们不会有如此顾忌
they have no such scruples.
- 安东尼 - 女士
- Antony! - Madam.
滚开 狗娘养的
Come down, you bastard!
女士 请吧
Madam, please!
你告诉我丈夫他是个废物人渣
You tell my husband that he's cowardly scum.
告诉他这些
Tell him that.
你了解的 显然 我们将失去所有的财产？
You realize, of course, we'll have to leave all our money behind.
- 我不在乎 - 我们将身无分文
- I don't care! - We're penniless.
我害怕 我想回家 快点
I'm scared. I want to go home. Please, hurry.
- 去哪儿？- 没有啊
- Going somewhere? - No.
不去哪 你怎么会这么认为？
No. What makes you think that?
求你了乌利纳斯.
Please, Vorenus.
别说出去 求你别说出去
Don't tell. Please don't tell.
对我们发发慈悲吧
Have mercy on us.
他们会杀了我们的 会把我们扔去喂鳄鱼
They'll kill us. They'll throw us to the crocodiles.
我妻子太紧张了
My wife is overwrought.
我们只是要去海港上闲逛
We were merely going to take a stroll along the harbor
去看看船
to look at the ships.
那么你们得快点了
Then you must hurry.
风向要变了 帆竖起来时看着还不错
The wind is changing. The ships look best when the sails are set.
和我们一起吧
Come with us.
- 不 - 战争就要打起来了
- No. - War is sure to come now.
这里不适合正派的罗马人待
This is no place for decent Romans.
是的 但我有责任
True, but I have responsibilities here.
时间到了
Now is the time.
如果你碰到提图斯.波罗
If you happen to see Titus Pullo,
让他帮我亲吻我的孩子们
ask him to kiss my children for me.
我会的
I will do that.
谢谢
Thank you.
你好 又见面了
Hello again.
很抱歉麻烦你们了
Sorry to trouble you.
你们介意我们藏在这里吗？
Would you mind awfully if we hide here
一直等到船驶入大海？
until this boat is at sea?
我记得的都告诉你了
I've told you everything I remember.
一定还有一些
There must be more than that.
看看你自己
Look to yourself.
你能使他记起一些事情
You are what remains of him.
乌利纳斯
Vorenus.
怎么样？
Well?
他们走了
They're gone.
好
Good.
阿提亚怎么样？
And how was... Atia?
我猜想她还是一贯的镇静吧？
I suppose she took it with her usual poise?
- 不是 - 不是？
- No. - No?
已经办好了
Well. Had to be done.
波士卡在哪 我叫他但他没来
Where's Posca? I sent for him but he did not come.
我不清楚 长官 你要我去看看吗
I don't know, sir. Do you wish me to go and look for him?
不 不
Oh, no, no.
就这样吧
It's all right.
我相信他会露面的
I'm sure he'll turn up.
长官 你妻子让我转告你一些话
Sir, your wife instructed me to tell you something.
她让我转告你 说你是个废物人渣
She instructed me to tell you that you are cowardly scum.
她这样说了？
She did, did she?
那… 你怎么看呢？
And... and what's your opinion of that?
这不是我能发表意见的话题 长官
It's not my place to have an opinion, sir.
说吧
Nah. Tell me anyway.
那是命令吗？
Is that an order?
是的 一个命令
Yes. That's an order.
你不是废物
You're no coward.
但你灵魂患了很严重的疾病
But you do have a strong disease in your soul.
它会吞噬你...
A disease that will eat away at you...
直到你死去
until you die.
真的？
Really?
是什么病？
And what is this disease?
我不知道 我又不是医生
I don't know. I'm not a doctor.
是啊
No.
是啊 你不是医生
No, you're not.
那你怎么能下如此诊断？
So how can you be so sure of your diagnosis, then?
我了解你的症状
I recognize your symptoms.
我也患了同样的病
I have the same sickness.
来个远投
Long one.
你好 妈妈 还有波士卡
Hello, Mother.
这个惊喜太让我高兴了
And Posca. What a pleasant surprise.
我召集了没被安东尼说服的人
I gather Antony was not amenable to persuasion.
不 他不会
No, he was not.
但你是知道的 不是吗
But you knew that, didn't you?
你想得到卡普里的一所别墅
You wanted a villa in Capri.
现在你能拥有了
Now you may have one.
屋达维娅还好吗？
Is Octavia well?
波士卡来这儿
Posca has something here
将帮你摧毁安东尼
that will help you destroy Antony.
- 妈妈 我希望… - 打倒安东尼和他的女王
- Mother, I am hoping... - Crush Antony and his queen.
你留着那该死的别墅吧
And you can keep your damn villa.
你有什么要给我的 波士卡？
You have something for me, Posca?
这是安东尼和克娄巴特拉
It is the last will and testament
最后意愿和遗嘱
of Antony and Cleopatra.
只会在他们死的时候才会公开和公布
To be opened and read only on the occasion of their death.
这是个可鄙的文件
It is a despicable document.
再加上他对你姐姐的批判
Taken together with his repudiation of your sister,
罗马人民一定会认为这次反安东尼的战争 虽然是不可避免的
the Roman people would think a war against Antony not only inevitable,
但是是非常合理的
but eminently desirable.
- 是真的吗 - 是真的
- Is it genuine? - It is genuine.
你是一个忠诚的好朋友 波士卡
You are a good and loyal friend, Posca.
这个已经能让他自我毁灭了
This one's cooked himself for dinner.
他说要死后要埋在亚历山大
He asks to be buried in Alexandria.
他宣布克娄巴特拉为他的妻子 他们已经住在一起了
He declares Cleopatra his wife and that they are living gods.
她是伊希斯女神 而他是奥斯里斯神
She is Isis and he, Osiris.
- 太棒了 - 等等 还有更好的
- It's perfect. - Wait, wait. It's better.
他留给他和克娄巴特拉的孩子 整个东部省
He leaves to his children by Cleopatra all the eastern provinces.
克娄巴特拉和恺撒的儿子
And her son by Caesar is to be given Rome and the west.
[罗马和西部]
已经抛弃了他亲爱的妻子 屋达维娅
Having rejected his loving wife Octavia,
马克.安东尼
Mark Antony has coupled himself
和那个女巫沆瀣一气
to the sorceress Cleopatra,
让她得到整个罗马的所有权
promising her dominion of all Rome!
他现在崇拜的是走狗和爬虫一类 卑鄙的人
He worships dogs and reptiles.
他的眼睛被烟灰熏黑了
He blackens his eyes with soot
像妓女一类的
like a prostitute.
他已经习惯低俗的尼罗河习俗
He dances and plays the cymbals
跳着舞还敲着钹
in vile Nilotic rites.
我知道你们有多么不开心 我也不会责怪你们
I know how unhappy you are and I cannot blame you.
当听说伟大的马克.安东尼 已经敬仰外来神
For who would not weep when he hears
抛妻弃子
that the great Mark Antony pays homage to foreign gods?
以及他的祖国
That he has abandoned his wife,
有谁能不伤心呢？
his child and his country?
有人问我是不是疯了 被魔法蛊惑
I am asked if he is gone mad, if he is bewitched.
我无法回答
I have no explanation.
我们可以为他哭泣 但也必须担起我们的责任
We may weep for him, but then we must do our duty,
因为他不再是一个罗马人 而是一个埃及人
for he is no longer a Roman, but an Egyptian.
除了战争我们还能做什么？
And what is left for us to do but fight him?
与他作战 毁灭他
Fight him and destroy him!
波罗 老朋友 真高兴看到你
Pullo. My old friend, it's good to see you.
- 长官 - 过来 坐
- Sir. - Come, sit down.
波士卡告诉我你的朋友乌利纳斯 甚至到现在还站在安东尼那边
Posca tells me our friend Vorenus stands by Antony even now.
忠心的乌利纳斯
Loyal man, Vorenus.
他让我问候你
He sends you his best regards,
请你为他亲吻他的孩子们
asked that you kiss his children for him.
- 他还好吧 - 你了解他的 坚如磐石
- He's all right, is he? - You know him. Iron as ever.
- 那你和他还是朋友了？- 是的
- You and he are still friends, then? - Yes.
我很快就会去东部 与安东尼作个了断
Very soon I will have to go east to end this thing with Antony.
我想你跟我一起去
I want you to come with me.
- 为什么 - 你和乌利纳斯关系很近
- Why? - You are close to Vorenus.
他和安东尼关系很近 你可以作个调停者
He is close to Antony. It may be you can act as a mediator.
那我们可能减少不必要的流血牺牲
Maybe we can save unnecessary bloodshed.
不是要和你争论 但情况似乎不是这样
Not to argue with you, but it doesn't seem likely.
当然有些是必须要死的 安东尼不能活
There are some will have to die, of course. Antony cannot be saved.
- 那个男孩恺撒里奥显然也必须去死 - 恺撒里奥？
- The boy Caesarion will have to go, obviously. - Caesarion?
他们已经公认他为罗马的国王了 波罗
They have named him putative king of Rome, Pullo.
他必须得死 但是克娄巴特拉以及她和安东尼的孩子
He will have to die but...
可能会留下
perhaps Cleopatra and her children by Antony may be saved.
- 为了稳定 - 是的
- Preserve some stability. - Yes.
我明白了
I see.
我不想命令你去 波罗 但如果不得不这样的话 我会这么做
I do not want to order you to come, Pullo, but I will if I have to.
不需要 没问题
No. No problem.
- 我会去 - 好的
- I'll come. - Good.
将会像古时候一样
It will be like old times.
一起历险
An adventure together.
因此或多或少是安东尼把屋大维拉到战争中去的
So, Antony more or less forced Octavian into war.
不然的话东部就会陷落于埃及人之手了 我们都不想那样 是吧
Else the east would be lost to the gyppos. We wouldn't want that, now would we?
崇拜一群猫狗 而你们有的是
Worshipping a bunch of dogs and cats and what have you.
总之 事情就是这样 屋大维命令我和他一起去
Any road, the thing is, Octavian's ordered me to go along with him.
所以我要做的就是和他一起去
So that's what I'll be doing. Going along with him.
- 能带上我吗 - 不 不能
- Can I come with you? - No. Sorry.
你和我待在这儿 我们都会没事的
You stay here with me. We'll be fine.
你们几乎没注意到我要走了
You'll hardly notice I'm gone.
好消息是…
And the good news is,
我很快就要见着你们的父亲了
I'm more than likely to see your father.
他带话说我要给你们每人一个他的亲吻
He sent word that I should give you all a kiss from him.
如果我见着他 能回给他一个亲吻吗
If I see him, can I give him a kiss from you in return?
不 他杀死了我们的母亲
No. He killed our mother.
是真的 不是吗
It's true, isn't it?
你很倔 你
You're a hard one, you.
是我父亲让我变成这样的
My father made me so.
我听说过
I hear you.
当我离开时 你们之间不会有矛盾了
While I'm away, there'll be no trouble between you.
别瞒报粮食配额 不要偷情
No skimming from the grain ration, no stealing of women,
也不要勒索 抢劫 或是纵火
nor any extortion, robbery, or arson...
除非得到马修斯的直接许可
unless under direct license by Mascius.
任何人越界的话
Anybody steps out of line,
将把他的食物与摩密奥分享
they'll be sharing their dinner with Memmio.
别忘了你的醋瓶
Don't forget your vinegar flask.
唔 是的
Right.
笑笑 不会去很久的
Give us a smile. Won't be gone forever.
如果你真爱我的话 你该带我一起去
If you really loved me, you'd take me with you.
这是战争 不是购物旅行
It's a war, not a shopping trip.
- 我能照顾好我自己 - 我知道你能
- I can take care of myself. - I know you can.
所以不担心你留在这儿
Which is why I'm not worried about leaving you here.
- 你现在要去哪？- 拿醋
- Where are you going now? - Vinegar.
摩密奥？
Memmio?
不可能是这样 不可能是这样
This is not happening. This isn't happening.
我都做了什么？
What have I done?
你为什么要这样惩罚我？
Why are you punishing me like this?
你这王八蛋 是我要死了
Oh, you selfish bastard. It's me who's dying.
不是惩罚你 是我
It's not you who's being punished, it's me.
我要死了
I'm gonna die.
这是因果报应
It is as... as it should be.
你曾经做过什么？你是个好女人
What have you ever done? You're a good woman.
现在不要为我而感伤
Don't get sentimental on me now.
有一件事 我不是个好女人
One thing I'm not is a good woman.
你已经对我很好了
You've been good to me.
不 我没有
No, I haven't.
伊莱尼
Eirene.
伊莱尼是个好女人 不像我是只母狼
Eirene was a good woman. Not a she-wolf like me.
- 她有她的优点 - 她就要给你生个孩子了
- She had her moments. - She was gonna give you a child.
命运的无奈
Fate had a different plan.
我们已经很幸福了 你和我
We're happy enough, you and me.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我不能死后还在心里存有谎言
I can't go to the afterlife with lies in my heart.
复仇女神让我无法休息
Nemesis won't let me rest.
什么谎言？
What lies?
为什么复仇女神要跟着你？
What's Nemesis want with you?
叫其他人走开
Send these people away.
都出去
Get out.
当我走后要记得
Remember when I'm gone,
我所做的
what I did,
对不起你的事
I did out of love for you.
做了什么？
Did what?
是我...
It was me
杀死了伊莱尼
who killed Eirene
和你的孩子
and your child.
我想得到你
I wanted you for myself.
所以我对她下了毒
So I poisoned her.
再见了 爱人
Goodbye, love.